<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Metamorphosis Christiana: or, The old man changed into the new. An occasional discourse.</title>
            <author>Beare, Nicholas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1563A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R172674</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097544</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097544</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171159</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2562:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Metamorphosis Christiana: or, The old man changed into the new. An occasional discourse.</title>
                  <author>Beare, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Collins in Essex-street, without Temple-Bar.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Nich. Beare.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 9-16 bound out of order (11-12, 9-10, 15-16, 13-14).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Metamorphoſis Chriſtiana:</hi> OR, THE OLD MAN Changed into the NEW. An Occaſional DISCOURSE.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Bene vixiſſe magnum eſt.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>He that Converteth a Sinner from the Errour of his Way, ſhall ſave a Soul from Death, and ſhall hide a multitude of Sins.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>James ult. ult.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Collins</hi> in <hi>Eſſex-ſtreet,</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:171159:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171159:2"/>
            <head>To the much Honoured, JOHN BASSET, <hi>Of</hi> Heanton-Court <hi>Eſquire, Recorder of the Town of</hi> Barn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, <hi>and Burgeſs for the ſame, Colonel of the North-Diviſion, and one of the Deputy-Lieutenants of</hi> Devon.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here preſent you with a Diſcourſe, which has no other pretence to your Patronage, but onely the good Intention wherewith it is offered: and (Sir) you may remember, that this hath ſometimes made <hi>a cup of cold water</hi> a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to a mighty King, acceptable; and preferred the <hi>two Mites</hi> of the poor Widow, as an Offering more grateful than much larger Gifts.</p>
            <p>Sir, the reaſon of this Addreſs proceeds not from an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of appearing <hi>in Print,</hi> for I have often declaimed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Scribbling of the Age; nor in ſatisfaction to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of Friends, the uſual pretence in the like caſes; nor yet purely in gratitude to thoſe many Favours you have obliged me withal, <hi>the Common-place and thred-bare Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dedications:</hi> Sir, I look'd back, and lo the too viſible Ruines of our late Contentions! I look'd forward, and ſaw the face of things tending much to the ſame way; I thought my ſelf concern'd to move toward the prevention of the <hi>growing evil,</hi> as knowing that an ordinary Phyſician and mean Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine may overcome a Diſeaſe in its <hi>beginnings;</hi> which being become <hi>chronical and inveterate,</hi> will triumph over the moſt <hi>exquiſite Preparations.</hi> So that the whole Plot drives at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the advancement of Peace and Love among Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Chriſtians; and, Sir, when I reſolved to adventure it abroad, to try mens eyes, and ſecond thoughts as well as ears, I preſently conſidered that Sphere wherein you ſtand, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding
<pb facs="tcp:171159:3"/>Influence you have with us, and withal, your own <hi>example,</hi> the patern of thoſe Vertues which you will find (though very imperfectly) deſcribed within. Whereupon I have preſumed to prefix your Name to the Front, as the ſureſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to make the Doctrine, at leaſt in its firſt and more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Deſign, ſucceſsful.</p>
            <p>Sir, I have no more to add, but this: <hi>May you be like your Father in every thing but ſhortneſs of days,</hi> is the devout prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Humble Servant,</hi> Nich. Beare.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171159:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Metamorphoſis Chriſtiana.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. ult.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>In Chriſt Jeſus neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but a new Creature.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMong the Beings of the lower World, that which gives Man the Preheminence is his Reaſon, that <hi>divine breath</hi> of the Almighty, which impowers him with the noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Will.</hi> Among Men that which chiefly exalts ſome above the reſt is <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Grace:</hi> there are other pretences which are eagerly contended for; the <hi>Jew</hi> talks much of the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> one of the peculiar Darlings of Heaven, upon whoſe account God cannot but reſpect his Off-ſpring, being by no leſs than a Miracle produced; and to this add by way of advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the plea of Circumciſion, the great and ſtable Precept (as they call it) of their Law, which in their opinion muſt exalt them above all mankind beſide. The more poliſhed <hi>Gentile</hi> does not a little vaunt of <hi>Athens,</hi> the ſeat of Learning; and having had his Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there, looks with ſcorn on the Inhabitants of any other part of <hi>Greece;</hi> and amongſt them moſt of all deſpiſes the <hi>Scythian</hi> to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb <hi>Barbarous.</hi> The man of Liberty derides him in Chains. Theſe by the Apoſtle are noted as the moſt remarkable pretences to Priori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all which he does here refell by an higher and more noble Claim, even the qualification of the Rent. 'Tis the not the Lineage of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> nor the loſs of the Fore-skin, not thy pretence of Education at the foot of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> nor thy living under the Doctrine of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Sage at <hi>Athens;</hi> not thy plea of Birth, nor that of Liberty: there is ſomewhat that will advance thee much beyond theſe, by which thou ſhalt outſhine other men, as the Moon does the leſſer Hoſt of Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> the new Creation in Chriſtianity, the <hi>All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither Greek nor Jew, Circumciſion nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, Barbarian, Scythian, bond nor free, but Chriſt is all and in all: and here neither Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion availeth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171159:4"/>
            <p>'Tis undeniably evident, that the great occaſion of this Epiſtle (as of many others) was the different Factions between the <hi>Jew</hi> and the <hi>Gentile,</hi> advanced by the falſe Prophets, and countenanced by the ſtaggering of the true; as is too notorious, not onely in the caſe of S. <hi>Peter</hi> here, in chap. 2. ver. 12. but alſo of the other Apoſtles, who (as S. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us) affirmed the neceſſity of Circumciſion, as a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification previous to the preaching and benefit of the Goſpel, untill S. <hi>Peter</hi> was by a Miracle convinced, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. and the truth by a Councel determined, chap. 15. It grieved S. <hi>Paul</hi> (as indeed it muſt a Miniſter of God) to ſee the preſent Church thus miſerably ſhattered; he thinks all his endeavours too little to heal thoſe <hi>ſores,</hi> he undertakes to his face the Head of the College, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.13. he not onely preaches down this as an Error, but in confutation writ with his own hand a large Epiſtle, wherein he ſets up this as his <hi>ſtandard,</hi> (like the Croſs with the Motto of <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) promiſing Victory here, he preſcribes this as the moſt ſovereign Balſam to heal their wounds, as the beſt Cement to knit and unite their Affections,—<hi>a new creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Scripture is the beſt Interpreter of it ſelf; who would be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſcantlings of the Chanel, when he may be admitted to the fulneſs of the Fountain? I ſhall give you therefore the ſenſe of the Text from theſe parallel places; <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Neither circumciſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but faith which worketh by love.</hi> Where (as the Learned <hi>Grotius</hi> notes) we are not to underſtand this grace ſingle, but in conjunction with others. Likewiſe from the 19 verſe to the end of the chapter, he gives us an account of the meaning of the Phraſe in <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.23. where he uſes theſe words, <hi>Put off concerning the former converſation the old man, which is corrupt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deceitful luſts, and be renewed in the ſpirit of your mind, and that ye put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſs and true holineſs.</hi> Where he further proceeds to a ſpecification of both, in a third Epiſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.8. where he expreſſeth himſelf thus: <hi>Put off all theſe, anger, wrath, malice, hlaſphemy.</hi>— And verſe 10. <hi>Put on the new man which is renewed in knowledge after the image of him that created him.</hi>— And verſe 12. <hi>Put on as the elect of God bowels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, kindneſs, humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, forbearing and forgiving one another.— And above all put on charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the whole (waving the preſent Controverſie) three things are to be conſidered:</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171159:4"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Somewhat here implied, which is to be put off, viz. the old man, or old creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What is here expreſſed (and elſewhere more formally commanded to be put on) the new creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The privilege and ſignificancy of this in Chriſtianity above any thing beſide; for in Chriſt Jeſus neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion, but a new Creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then we are to conſider what is here implied and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and is to be put off, <hi>viz.</hi> the old man, which is ſet forth in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture by theſe phraſes, <hi>the body of ſin, the law of the members, the works of darkneſs, the natural man, the members that are upon earth,</hi> and the like; which gives us no ſmall light to the right Underſtanding of the firſt thing. The old man is made up of the maſs of that ſin which was the product of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion.</p>
            <p>And here I deſign not to give you an account of all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; that would be a task too tedious; but becauſe I find ſome more principally by the Apoſtle recited in the places foregoing, and for the reaſon following, I ſhall glance on theſe four, <hi>Pride, Malice, Anger, Envy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are not to look on theſe as ſingle or common vices; they are chief <hi>Commanders,</hi> they have <hi>teeming wombs,</hi> and like the <hi>Trojan Horſe,</hi> ſtock the world with Troops, if not Regiments of other Evils; and hence, hence are the Iliads of our miſeries.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Pride</hi> in a ſtrict ſenſe is a ſpecial ſin, as the great Schoolman
<note n="*" place="margin">22 <hi>ae. q.</hi> 162.</note> has noted, in regard it has a proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which muſt ſpecifie and diſtinguiſh it; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſidered with reſpect to its <hi>prolifick</hi> nature, it may be fitly called the
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Regina &amp; Mater.</hi> Ib.</note> 
               <hi>Empreſs</hi> and <hi>Parent</hi> of all ſins; though not neceſſarily ſo, as is obſerved by the ſame <hi>Aquinas</hi> out of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> ſins ſometimes receiving their original from other cauſes; yea even in its moſt peculiar reſpect, it has no leſs than four monſtrous parts, verſe 5. 1. The proud man thinks, that the goodneſs which he has is not derivative, but from himſelf alone. 2. That what benefits he does enjoy are the products of his own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. 3. He boaſts that he has what he has not. And 4. Deſpiſing all other men he covets alone to have what he doth deſire.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Malice.</hi> This has its proper Seat in the <hi>Will,</hi> and therefore muſt be acknowledged to be the Principle of all the depravity of our actions proceeding thence; this is that poiſon which corrupts the Fountain, and cannot but make the Streams unwholeſom; the <hi>indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171159:5"/>the <hi>deſign,</hi> the <hi>reſolution</hi> of ſinning, that ſin which bends and ſets men up for miſchief.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The next is <hi>Anger,</hi> which may be allowed of, if it be kept cloſe to its proper Object, and within its due bounds, <hi>(Be angry, but ſin not)</hi> yet cannot but be hugely ſinful and deſtructive, when it has received infection from the aforeſaid <hi>Leaven:</hi> when like a River it ſwells be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its proper Chanel; or like the overflowings of the Gall, which at once diſcolours and diſaffects the whole body. This Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may not unfitly be reſembled unto Fire, of good Uſe in its right ſphere, but when it has exceeded that, threatens nothing below the certain ruine of our own, if not others Houſes. Of this there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kinds,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22 <hi>ae. q.</hi> 150.</note> according to the different Conſtitutions of men; and no leſs than ſeven <hi>Daughters,</hi> if we may credit <hi>Gregory;</hi> though (I think) upon due examination her Iſſue will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be much more numerous.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The laſt is <hi>Envy,</hi> which I term the Canker of the Breaſt, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption got by the thriving of others;
<note place="margin">22 <hi>ae. q.</hi> 36.</note> this alſo is fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and parturient of many other Vices.</p>
            <p>Theſe I have mentioned as the vital and principal parts of the old man, like the four Elements to the body natural; and as there can be no compoſition without the union of theſe, ſo we ſhall find the other conſpiring in a mixture to make up the conſtitution of the preſent ſinner.</p>
            <p>We are told, that while <hi>Julia</hi> lived, the Daughter of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and Wife to <hi>Pompey,</hi> and <hi>Craſſus,</hi> by whoſe triple League and Friendſhip the two other Generals were kept aſunder, as the <hi>Ionean</hi> and <hi>Aegean</hi> Seas by the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Corinth;</hi> but they are no ſooner removed, but the Trumpet ſounds to Battel, which ends in the certain ruine of one, and the deſtruction of the greateſt Empire that ever the world ſaw. Thus when men caſt off the obligations of <hi>Nature, Friendſhip,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> and give reins to theſe, what other Iſſue can be expected, but that theſe wilde Steeds (like the Horſes of the Sun) ſet the world on fire? Theſe open the Floud-gates to all our Contentions and Diviſions, whether publick or private. I am bold to aſſert, that there was never any diſturbance ſince the world began, wherein one (if not more of theſe) was not more immediately concerned in the quarrel. The true origine this of all Wars between Princes on one ſide or t'other; of leſſer Wars, that is to ſay, Law-ſuits between man and man; the Source of all the Contentions, Diviſions, Factions, Schiſms, Hereſies, Lying, Slandering, Back-biting, Obloquy, and of a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171159:5"/>thouſand other Evils. Theſe make our Hearts Cages of unclean Birds, our Actions virulent, and our Tongues no other than the Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands of Hell. Who then but muſt conclude for the putting of them off?</p>
            <p>For our encouragement in which work we cannot want Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which way ſoever we caſt our Eyes. Look we abroad, and lo what deſolation theſe have made! No Age, no Empire, no Miſery which gives us not ſufficient Teſtimonies of its Spoils. I will not begin to give you Examples for the proof, leſt I ſhould not eaſily make an end: and I ſuppoſe it needleſs to travel either far back or abroad, for that which we may meet with at our own doors. Look we then round about us, and ſee what havock theſe have made! The <hi>old man</hi> carries a large and diſorderly Retinue at his heels, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be entertained but with great coſt and trouble; and if not ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off the ſooner, will inevitably bankrupt his hoſts in the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The proud man thinks nothing too much that may conduce to the keeping up or advancing his Grandeur. The envious and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious will not be ſparing in any thing that may do hurt to their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; he will be content to loſe one eye, that his Adverſarie may be bereft of both.</p>
            <p>The paſſionate man puts all at ſtake for Satisfaction, though the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front were but a trifle.</p>
            <p>See how effectually Diviſions and Controverſies do weaken; like the Duel of the Frog and the Mouſe in the Epilogue, they drew bloud ſo long of each other, as that an Enemy has the advantage, and the quarrel ends in the deſtruction of both. Liſten we to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the thred-bare Client! you may learn the ſtate of his Purſe by his habit; his countenance does betray the grievance of his heart; and 'tis ten to one but that the Suit commenced from one of theſe. How many Eſtates are there round about us, that upon this account have changed their Names; and many that nod and totter? How me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick men return from <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> where the Victor is ſure to be a Loſer? What Slaves men make themſelves to dance at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, and wait the pleaſure of the meaneſt Officers of the Law? How vaſtly like a Snow-ball Paſſion advances, ſo that that which in the beginning was not worth the regarding, within a while becomes the ſubject of an irreconcileable feud; ſo true is that of the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> 3.5. <hi>How great a matter a little fire kindleth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is it deſtructive without, and upon examination we ſhall find that it makes no ſmall diſturbance within. The Off-ſpring of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171159:6"/>the <hi>old man</hi> may not unfitly be reſembled to the products of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, which eat their way out through their Mothers Bowels: or as the Serpent in the Fable, they will requite our kindneſs with poiſon: or as we read in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. his operations are like thoſe of that unclean ſpirit there, it oftentimes throws the poſſeſſed into the <hi>fire,</hi> and into the <hi>water,</hi> drives them to contrary inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
            <p>Behold the malitious and envious man, how <hi>thin, meager,</hi> and <hi>pale</hi> is he! He cannot hear of the good of another, but his ears will <hi>tingle;</hi> he cannot ſee him thriving without tears or dimneſs, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think of it without <hi>melancholy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold the angry and paſſionate, and during the <hi>Paroxyſm</hi> what is he but a perfect mad man? It makes men look dreadful, according to the obſervation of the wiſe Heathen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antoninus de ſeipſo, l.</hi> 7. <hi>ſec.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>An angry counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is much againſt Nature, and is oftentimes the proper coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of them that are at the point of death.</hi> We muſt conclude the pain within, from the diſorderly looks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; the violence of the Waves from the froth and noiſe which they ſend forth.</p>
            <p>Behold the proud perſon! and lo every diſappointment that he meets withal puts him upon the Rack, unhinges him from all his other enjoyments, and takes away the comforts of his life.</p>
            <p>To exemplifie this by an Inſtance or two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ahab</hi> a King, and therefore no ways needing the ſmall portion of Ground, the native Inheritance of the poor <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> yet when he had ſet his heart upon it, and had ſpoken to <hi>Naboth</hi> about it, and being denied it, and ſo defeated in his deſign: ſee what a damp is put upon his ſpirits; ſo the Text tells us, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.4. <hi>Ahab came into his houſe heavy and diſpleaſed, becauſe of the word which Naboth the Jeſreelite had ſpoken unto him; and he laid him down upon his bed, and he turned away his face and would eat no bread.</hi> In like ſort we find it in the caſe of <hi>Haman,</hi> he is the great and ſupreme Favourite in the Court of <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> he obtains whatſoever he asks of him; in his paſſage from his Houſe to the Palace, he obſerved the irreverent carriage of a <hi>Jew,</hi> he did not bow and cringe as his Highneſs expected; whereupon he is ſo much moved as to ſwear the deſtruction of the whole Race; a deſign inhumanly barbarous and unreaſonable, had the affront been a thouſand times greater, but he is reſolv'd; <hi>(Pride and Paſſion when let looſe know no bounds;)</hi> he goes on with his purpoſe; ſends forth an Edict through all parts of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171159:6"/>the Kingdom, to kill on a certain day all the <hi>Jews,</hi> without the leaſt exception or reſerve. Here it might have been expected, that he ſhould have reſted ſatisfied, having obtained for his purpoſe a Law which is called <hi>unalterable;</hi> but 'tis otherwiſe; his extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Advancement, Riches, and Favour of ſitting uſually at the Kings Table, (ſeldom to Subjects vouchſafed) are fruitleſs and inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant; he has no Appetite to the Kings meat; he ſits <hi>in ſtate</hi> as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>thorns,</hi> and for no other reaſon but becauſe the already condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Jew</hi> remains yet at the Gate alive: for thus it is recorded, <hi>Heſter</hi> 5.11, <hi>&amp;c. And Haman told them of the glory of his riches, and the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his children, and all the things wherein the King had promoted him; how he had advanced him above the Princes and Servants of the King. And Haman ſaid moreover, Yea Heſter the Queen let no man come in with the King unto the banquet which ſhe had prepared, but my ſelf; and tomorrow I am invited unto her alſo with the King. Yet all this availeth me nothing, as long as I ſee</hi> Mordecai <hi>the Jew ſitting at the Kings gate.</hi> 'Twere eaſie to manifeſt the like by running through every part of the <hi>old man,</hi> ſtill carrying grief and malady where ever he goes; the ſinner is ſubject to <hi>heart-burnings</hi> and <hi>ſtrong convulſions,</hi> the gripings of the Guts, the gnawings of the Liver, which ſome have affirmed the Onely, all ſuppoſe it the Greateſt puniſhment of Hell it ſelf. Thus (like him in the Comedian) he is his own Tormentor, go he where he will, betake himſelf to what he pleaſes, he carries his Plague along with him. Theſe Fiends (like the evil Spirit of <hi>Saul</hi>) are his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Attendants; they haunt him at his Table, and take away his Stomach; await him at his Bed, and ſcare him with Conflicts and Rencounters in his dreams. The fruit of the forbidden Tree, though it be pleaſant to the eye, ſavours of nothing but Gall in the concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the ſin of <hi>Gomorrah</hi> produces no other fruit but that of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Remedies which in this caſe may be preſcribed, are ſo vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as that 'tis difficult to put a period to this firſt part. Conſider we the Senſitive Creatures, and though they are not without their paſſions, yet they ſeldom or never exert them to the diſturbance ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of themſelves or their Societies. See what a joynt harmony there is among the Individuals of every kind: The Beaſts of prey are not at variance among themſelves;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antoninus lib.</hi> 11. <hi>Sect.</hi> 16.</note> the Venomous Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpit not poiſon at each other. Hear the great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher and Emperour, <hi>Neither Bees do it one to another, nor any other creatures that are naturally ſociable.</hi> Which in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171159:7"/>his Opinion proves his aſſertion, namely, <hi>that we were not born to hurt and annoy one another,</hi> the great deſign of Malice and Paſſion. Theſe actually violating the ſacred Tyes of Friendſhip, and diſturbing that ſweet communion which ought to be among men. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he goes on,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>To be angry is not the part of a man, but to be meek and gentle ſounds of Manhood;</hi> and concludes, that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Paſſion proceed from Weakneſs.</p>
            <p>To the ſame effect doth the Scholar of <hi>Epictetus</hi> exellently rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arrian. in Epict. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Paſſion doth diſparage and degrade, turns the Man into a Viper:</hi> whoſe actions ought not to move thee, rather ſhouldeſt thou pity ſuch a one, as we do thoſe that are <hi>blind, deaf,</hi> and <hi>lame,</hi> men under great Imperfections and Deformities. Should I do well to take notice of the barking of every little Dog as I paſs the ſtreets?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antoninus lib.</hi> 7. <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag.</hi> 19.</note> to be offended with a <hi>blind</hi> man for taking the wall of me? or of a <hi>deaf</hi> man becauſe he doth not hear me? or of an <hi>Ideot</hi> becauſe I cannot by reaſon perſwade him? The Ancients allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the liberty of Paſſion, or at leaſt no <hi>extravagancy</hi> thereof, to vertuous men; and indeed it implies no leſs than a contradiction, that Reaſon ſhould ſit as ſupreme in that Breaſt where Anger, Malice, Pride, and ſuch like bear ſway. Theſe are to be handled as Beaſts of great ſtrength and violence, to be reſerved in chains, and kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in due bounds, for, exſpatiating they will become deſtructive. As thou art a Being endowed with Underſtanding, thou ſhouldeſt be careful to preſerve a Calm, as knowing that Winds and Storms will expoſe thy Veſſel at preſent to ſtrange motions and diſorders, and to <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> in the concluſion. And as the Ship bound for <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> by reaſon of the Fugitive was overtaken with a ſtorm, not to be appeaſed with any expedients the Mariners could think on, but onely by throwing the rebellious Prophet over-board: So here, as long as the old ſinner ſways within, we can expect no Quiet; this muſt ſucceed, his being committed to the deep. This Reaſon doth ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p>And if it be not fully convincing, have we recourſe to the <hi>infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> directions of our Religion!</p>
            <p>Hear how the Angel does beſpeak the devout Women, <hi>He is not here, he is riſen: why ſeek ye the living among the dead?</hi> Upon our admiſſion to Diſcipleſhip we are to forſake the Tombs, and to ſhake off the condition of <hi>filth and rottenneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171159:8"/>
            <p>Liſten to the Doctrine of our Saviour, <hi>No man can ſerve two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; for either he will hate the one and love the other, or elſe he will hold to the one and deſpiſe the other: he cannot ſerve God and Mammon.</hi> As in Baptiſm, thoſe that were to be dip'd, upon their return from the Water, did change their Cloaths, and put on clean attire; ſo muſt every Chriſtian in a Spiritual Senſe. I make this Compariſon the rather becauſe the Learned <hi>Grotius</hi> doth aſſure us, that the Phraſes of <hi>Putting off</hi> and <hi>Putting on,</hi> have reference to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Cuſtome, as alſo becauſe I find this to be the Subject of our <hi>Baptiſmal Vow,</hi> as in our <hi>Church-Catechiſm</hi> is excellently expreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That I ſhould renounce the Devil and all his Works, the Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World, and all the ſinful Luſts of the Fleſh—that I ſhould keep God's Holy Will and Commandments, and walk in the ſame all the days of my Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then we deſign to embrace this Religion, and really to be what we profeſs, we muſt not only ſwear, but procure the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of theſe <hi>Diſorderly Paſſions:</hi> the Sinner muſt be driven out, that the Saint may be brought into poſſeſſion: the <hi>Old Man</hi> muſt die, that the <hi>New Creature</hi> may grow and proſper, which brings me to my ſecond Part.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But a New Creature.</head>
               <p>FOr the true meaning of which, let us (as before) conſider thoſe parallel expreſſions whereby 'tis ſet forth in Scripture, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times under the notion of <hi>Regeneration,</hi> as in our Saviour's diſcourſe with <hi>Nicodemus;</hi> ſometimes by the Phraſe of the <hi>New Man;</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where by the Armour of Light; the whole Armour of God. The putting on of Chriſt <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Fruits of the Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort then, this is one of thoſe Scripture-Phraſes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Crell. Ech. Chriſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap</hi> 3. <hi>in.</hi>
                  </note> by which Piety in its moſt comprehenſive ſenſe is ſet forth, for which there is undeniable Evidence to be produced, becauſe the Spirit in Scripture in the Deſcription of the <hi>New Creature</hi> or <hi>New Man,</hi> in many places mentions thoſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which we owe to God, our ſelves, and one another, as parts or effects thereof.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe this compriſes the whole of our Religion, it may not be expected that I ſhould run through every particular, and becauſe I find in the parallel place, inſtead of a <hi>New Creature,</hi> Faith <hi>which worketh by Love.</hi> ch. 5.6. and becauſe our Love to our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171159:9"/>is the beſt Argument and Expreſſion of our Love towards God; as St. <hi>John</hi> in his Epiſtles excellently reaſons. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as (<hi>Col.</hi> 3.12, 13.) I find ſome more particularly mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: <hi>Put on therefore Bowels of Mercies, Kindneſs, Humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering, Forbearing, and Forgiving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>— if any have a Quarrel at any; <hi>and above all put on Charity.</hi> I ſhall touch at theſe: laying down this as a ſure Foundation, <hi>That the beſt Evidence we make a Conſcience of our Duties towards God and our ſelves, that we engage in publick Duties out of a true Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and are not wanting in our cloſeſt Devotions is, ourrſtving in the due Diſcharge of thoſe we owe to one another:</hi> the ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is <hi>Bowels of Mercies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which we are to underſtand no mean or common Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no <hi>Superficial Outſide-love,</hi> but that of the Bottom of the Heart, as appears from the frequent Uſe of the <hi>Word</hi> (<hi>Job</hi> 38.36. <hi>ch.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.31.) being put for our Heart, the Seat of our Love and Affection; ſo that the Apoſtle requires here Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in its higheſt and moſt intenſe degree, ſuch a Carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our Fellow-Creatures, as is of the Lord in the Parable (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.) to his Servant; he uſes no Methods of extream rigour, he does not take him by the Throat, and hale him to Priſon, to the ruine of himſelf, and Family; but being affected with his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, forgives him the Debt.</p>
               <p>Nor ſuch a regardleſs carriage as the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Levite</hi> ſhewed to the robbed and wounded Way-faring-man; (touched with no pity at the ſight of an Object able to have moved an Heart of Stone.)</p>
               <p>But like that of the good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> who no ſooner ſees him, but <hi>melts</hi> towards him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.33. as it clearly appears by what he does for him; <hi>binds up his Wounds, pours Wine and Oyl, puts him upon his own Horſe, carries him to an Inn, entertain'd him during his abode there, and makes Proviſion for him after his departure.</hi> The moſt genuine effects of this Vertue.</p>
               <p>And, to add one Inſtance more, like that of the Father, to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal Son (<hi>Luke</hi> 15.20.) he had Compaſſion on him, <hi>the ſame Word,</hi>— He was affected with his Miſery; his Words Tears, and Poverty conſtrained him to Pity and Relief; how lovingly doth he receive him! he ran, fell on his Neck, and kiſſed him; how nobly does he entertain him! <hi>Calls for the beſt Garment, for a Ring, Shoes, the Fatted Calf is ſlain, and there is Feaſting, Muſick, and Dancing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171159:7"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> whereby I underſtand that Vertue which does di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us in our Converſation, a ſweetneſs and pleaſantneſs in our Diſcourſe and Behaviour; not to carry Frowns in our Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, not to be bitter in our Words, nor moroſe in our Actions; in Company to betray no ill Humour, not to mourn in an Houſe of Feaſting, nor to laugh in one of Mourning; but in things Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Civil and Convenient to be Conformable: this our Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as well as our Religion doth require. So that they are much miſtaken, who conceive that Chriſtianity doth oblige us to the Sullenneſs of a <hi>Stoick</hi> or an <hi>Anchorite,</hi> to live like <hi>Diogenes</hi> under his <hi>Tub,</hi> or the Hermit in his Cell.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Humbleneſs of Mind;</hi> a Vertue this which curbs us in the too eager purſuit of Honour, directs us to entertain low Thoughts of our ſelves, and high of other men. Which practis'd, would be of ſovereign Uſe in our Converſation. How many thouſand Diſputes are there at this time about Precedencie in the World, among all <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Degrees?</hi> Our hearts are naturally apt to ſwell, and the Tempter (as of old) does endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to advance us to the Pinacle of the Temple. The Humour of the Scribes and Phariſees (noted by our Saviour <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.6.) is Epidemical; We are too apt to love <hi>the uppermoſt Rooms at Feaſts, and the chief Seats in the Synagogues, and greetings in the Markets, and to be called of Men</hi> Rabbi, Rabbi. This very Leaven had ſometimes infected the very Apoſtles themſelves; they diſputed who amongſt them ſhould be the greateſt, each contending for Supremacy; now as an Antidote, what doth Chriſt preſcribe but this Vertue? and for their Encouragement, in his own example writes them a Copy, <hi>John</hi> 13.15.</p>
               <p>We ought not to look on our ſelves and parts through a <hi>Teleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope,</hi> nor to behold the Deſerts of others through a <hi>Microſcope;</hi> but to make uſe of the Looking-glaſs of the Prophet, which ſets us out in our proper Colours, tells us what we <hi>were, are and ſhall be,</hi> ( <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ) <hi>Earth, Earth, Earth;</hi> what we are made of, what at preſent we are, and what ſhortly we ſhall be reduced un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Thus let us caſt Duſt on our Heads, and then (as has been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of the Bees) <hi>Hi motus animorum atque haec certa:</hi> moſt if not all our Contentions would vaniſh.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> a quiet and peaceable Calmneſs which reſtrains from Anger and Revenge, which moderates and puts bounds to juſt Puniſhment. A Grace this which goes in conjunction with Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, and though in its formalitie it be none of the <hi>Capital Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:171159:8"/>yet it diſpoſeth to theſe; one of the great Beatitudes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 157. <hi>qu.</hi>
                  </note> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.5.) and that which is highly requiſite and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous for all Degrees of Men, <hi>v.g.</hi> the Governour and Great man, that he do not cruſh thoſe that are below him; the Equal, that he do not uſurp; and the Inferior, that he behave himſelf with proportion to his Qualitie. Of this Vertue there are many <hi>Offices, Properties,</hi> and many Rules to be obſerved; but thoſe I wave, as being not of this place to examine.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Long-ſuffering;</hi> We are not upon every occaſion to be ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moved, upon the leaſt diſtaſt forthwith to commence War; with the Diſciples, to call preſently for Fire to burn our Enemies, (<hi>Luke</hi> 9.57.) but to wait a while with patience: <hi>That may be done anon, which cannot poſſibly for the preſent be effected;</hi> in this caſe we ſhould propoſe as a <hi>Pattern</hi> the <hi>Lord of the Vineyard,</hi> Luke 13. who for ſome years withheld the <hi>Ax</hi> from the Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Tree, and gave it, in hopes of Improvement, all the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Husbandry: looking up (which is the great Deſign of that Parable) to the wonderful Patience and Forbearance of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme God, who, <hi>Though he be provoked every day, does not inſtantly whet his Sword, bend his Bow, and prepare his Arrows within his Quiver.</hi>—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Forbearing and Forgiving one another;</hi> Offences will ariſe; even among Chriſtians there may be cauſes of Controverſies; but 'tis very unfit, that ſuch ſhould behave themſelves in their Differences like the <hi>Heathen;</hi> the Apoſtle requires in them thoſe Vertues which make them prone to be reconciled; in order whereunto, obſerve what a ſtrong Reaſon he backs his Exhortation withal. <hi>Forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another</hi> and <hi>Forgiving one another;</hi> my Brother has offended me now; one time or other, I may, and in all probability ſhall offend him (for in many things we offend all) therefore I muſt be willing and ready to forgive, that I may be upon occaſion for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given: yea the Forgiveneſs of his Offence, is in effect the pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my own; without which I could not in reaſon expect it. A weighty Argument this, and frequently by the Apoſtle urged, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Brethren, if a Man be overtaken in a Fault, ye which are Spiritual reſtore ſuch an one in the Spirit of Meekneſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering thy ſelf leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot by any means ſide with them who have deemed all Wars for Chriſtians unlawful. I have learn'd, <hi>That the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Prince, the Juſtice of the Cauſe, the Sincerity of the Intention,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171159:10"/>make even an offenſive War beyond all exception juſtifiable. Much leſs can I ſide with them who ſuppoſe that Chriſtianity doth manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, take men off from all other Law; for which opinion they produce the Abrogation of the <hi>Lex talionis,</hi> the ſtanding Law, not only of the <hi>Jews,</hi> but all other Nations. — And the ſubſequent Words, <hi>That ye reſiſt not Evil; but whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on the Right Cheek, turn to him the other alſo; and if any man will ſue thee at the Law, and take away thy Coat, let him have thy Cloak alſo.</hi> — Mat. 5.39. and that Paſſage of the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1, 7. <hi>Dare any of you, having a matter againſt another, go to Law before the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt? — Now therefore there is utterly a Fault amongſt you, becauſe ye go to Law one with the other, why do you not rather take wrong? why do you not ſuffer your ſelves to be defrauded? Nay you do wrong and defraud, and that your Brethren.</hi> For there are of great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Church, who tell us, that the intent of our Saviour, in that part of his Sermon forementioned, was not to tie up the Hands of the Magiſtrate, but to take men off from Revenge and private <hi>Retaliation;</hi> and that the aforeſaid Law is not in every particular ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated, appears in many caſes; but that more eſpecially of Murther, where Blood is required for Blood; and that the ſubſequent Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are not to be underſtood literally,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Lib. de Ser. Dom. in mont.</hi>
                  </note> is plain (as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> reaſons) from the Practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: for he did not turn the Left Cheek to him that ſmote him on the Right, but made ſome reſiſtance, <hi>John</hi> 18.23. and the like we find of St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 23.3. and <hi>ch.</hi> 16.37.</p>
               <p>And for anſwer to the other place, the Apoſtle (as appears from the whole Text) does not ſimply condemn the Law, but the <hi>Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity</hi> in the Uſe thereof: he checks the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for being too forward and haſty to engage in Law, and for appealing to the Tribunals of Infidels, for the determination of their Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</p>
               <p>Chriſtianity does not require of her Proſelytes, that they be eaſie Fools to part with their Poſſeſſions without the leaſt Reſiſtance. Religion is not deſtructive of each Mans Propriety, of which the Law is Judge, or rather the Rule, without which there would be no living in the World. If this frantick Poſition were admitted, moſt Chriſtians would publickly be reduced to a condition like (if not worſe than) that of the twelve Apoſtles, be, not only without <hi>Variety of Garments,</hi> but want <hi>neceſſary Cloathing; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171159:11"/>Gold and Silver, and Money in their Purſes.</hi> If ſo, the command of ſelling all that they had was needleſs; and not only ſome Men of an order, but the whole Religion, would in a ſhort time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Mendicants.</hi> The ſame Apoſtle teacheth us that the Law is good, if a Man uſe it lawfully, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.8. and how that is to be done for a Right underſtanding of the preſent <hi>Rule, How, When,</hi> and <hi>Whom</hi> we ought to <hi>Forbear</hi> and <hi>Forgive.</hi> In this as its pro per place may be reſolved, the Subject of theſe four following Conditions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Cond. Chriſtians were not to uſe the Law with Delight and Study.</hi> There are ſome, who (like the <hi>Salamanders</hi>) covet to live in the Fire; are out of their Element, if they are not themſelves fighting, or ſetting others by the Ears. Men o'regone with the Itch of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, who love the noiſe of <hi>Courts,</hi> and think their time mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent, if ſome buſineſs does not call them to the Aſſizes; who deem it an Argument of Generoſity to enter the Liſt, and be perpetually ſtrugling with Enemies. An humour this, very oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the peaceable Ties of Chriſtianitie in general, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to the preſent Direction of Forbearing and Forgiving one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. A Practice ſo noxious, as that the Law does not only <hi>brand,</hi> but make proviſion for its puniſhment, and that in more Sences than one, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch who ſhall <hi>incite, perſwade</hi> and <hi>egg</hi> others on to wage Law: and ſuch likewiſe, who themſelves ſhall diſturb others by frequent and vexatious Law-ſuits, ranking both under the name of Barretors; who without any wrong may be called the Caterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Nation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Cond. That Law ought to be uſed not as the firſt, but as the laſt Remedie.</hi> Law-Suits may not unfitly be compared to the <hi>Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-glaſſes, Scarifyings, and Salivations of the Phyſitian, to the Knife and Saw of the Chirurgeon:</hi> means never uſed but in deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Caſes, and as the laſt Remedies. What elſe is inculcated by thoſe Heavenly Directions? If it be poſſible as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18. <hi>Studie to be quiet,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.11. <hi>and endeavouring to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</hi> Eph. 4.3. and Rom. 14.19. Heb. 12.14. All which Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions carry an Elegance in the Original, requiring our utmoſt Induſtry. As in matters of Scandal, ſo alſo in Wrongs, we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that Method by our Saviour propoſed <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15. <hi>If thy Brother ſhall treſpaſs againſt thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him alone; if he ſhall hear thee thou haſt gained thy Brother; —
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171159:9"/>but if he will not hear thee, then take with thee one or two more;—and if he ſhall neglect to hear them, tell it to the Church.</hi> — Upon any wrong we are privately to reaſon the Caſe and demand Redreſs, if this Expedient do not ſucceed: in the next place we are to uſe the Aſſiſtance of a good Friend or two; and when they cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, we may lawfully appeal to the Magiſtrate for Relief. If this Courſe were taken (which our Religion directs us to) how many Controverſies would die in their Abortion? how much Charge to our ſelves, and Trouble to others would be prevented? what? (ſaith the Apoſtle) is there not a wiſe Man amongſt you?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aq.</hi> 12. <hi>q.</hi> 2.</note> not one that can judge between his Brethren? 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.5. The Law is founded upon Reaſon, <hi>Humane</hi> Law upon the Law of <hi>Nature.</hi> Whereupon I conceive it poſſible for Men whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant of the Law in its formalitie, to be able to decide aright; and if the Caſe be a proper Caſe of Law, why may not the Advice of the Learned therein (the matter on both ſides being rightly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) be as effectual as their Pleading at the Bar, and the <hi>Verdict</hi> of twelve Men, that certainly are not Infallible, that may be either ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant or reſolute? For my part I know not why theſe, or ſuch like means being uſed, moſt Controverſies among Chriſtians may not with leſſer Noiſe, leſſer Charge, and far leſſer Inconvenience be ended at home. If after all theſe, men will be unreaſonable, ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be delivered over to the Law to be ſeverely <hi>ſcourged.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Cond. Law-ſuits are not to be commenc'd about Trifles.</hi> 'Tis not to be conceived amidſt Societies, where Eſtates are contiguous, but that there will be mutual Treſpaſſes: now for ſuch to contend, would be highly unreaſonable; if I am treſpaſſed to day, I may be a Treſpaſſer to morrow. How much then am I concern'd to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the Commencing of a Suit, which in the conſequence muſt fall heavy on my ſelf, and open a Gap to endleſs Controverſies? How much rather ſhould I have recourſe to the preſent advice of Forbearing and Forgiving one another, and declare by my Practice, that in my Prayers I am not guilty either of <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> or <hi>Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</hi> 'Tis no ſmall Scandal to that Religion, whoſe Badge is <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> to behold its Proſelytes like <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Wolves</hi> in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, taking each other by the Throat for a thing of an inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable value, heaping no ſmall Trouble and Charges to themſelves and others; and that to the advantage of none but the <hi>Lawyer.</hi> Whoever will be pleaſed to make the obſervation, ſhall eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the great abuſe of the Law. In this regard the occaſion too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171159:10"/>
                  <hi>de Lana Caprina, pedibus ambulando</hi> &amp;c. ſome pitiful worthleſs thing, which whether had or loſt makes not a farthing odds. Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine we the ancient Records, and have recourſe to the preſent Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, and we ſhall have very many and undeniable Arguments to confirm us in the preſent abuſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Cond. To go to Law in Love, and to deſign nothing in the Suit but Relief:</hi> this is a neceſſary though it be a difficult Condition, and as is too apparent from the general practices of men, ſeldome or never obſerved; for no ſooner is an Action brought, but that the Parties Litigant ſet forth their Flags of Defiance to each other, — forgetting they are Chriſtians, yea Men. How many Caſes are there, wherein the Law is made Uſe of only as a <hi>Pretence,</hi> a <hi>Pandar</hi> to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Envy, an Inſtrument taken up for no other end, but to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the ruine of an Adverſarie. I wiſh the World would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me of Falſhood here; but I fear 'tis ſo manifeſt, as that it will on all hands be granted without any denial. What's that which ſet the <hi>Roman</hi> Generals by the Ears, but the Pride of each others Hearts, and their Emulation? — And we are likewiſe told, that an old grudge was the true cauſe of all thoſe Vexations which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel the <hi>Trojans.</hi> — I leave the Application of theſe Heathen-paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to you. — There muſt be ſome Pretence to Juſtifie the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie in Court, a Treſpaſs, a Priviledge, a Title. Whereas with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the Curtain, and (in all likelihood) you ſhall diſcover an <hi>old Sore</hi> within: the Furies will appear in their proper Colours, and where theſe bear Sway, 'tis no difficult matter to find out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what that ſhall ſet the Wheels a going. If <hi>Jezebel</hi> be diſpoſed to take away at once the Life and Vineyard of <hi>Naboth,</hi> ('tis an eaſie matter to find a Staff to beat a Dog,) the Devil will quickly put her into the Road-way, direct her to proclaim a Faſt, and procure Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> for her purpoſe. When Men will be quarrelſome, they ſhall not want Pretences. Under this Head, thoſe great Men are highly to be charged, who depending on their Power, will not do that which is juſt, but wearie the mean Man out by Law. Such alſo who deſign not ſo much <hi>Satisfaction</hi> to themſelves in Law-ſuits, as <hi>Trouble, Charge,</hi> and <hi>Ruine</hi> to their Adverſaries. And ſuch like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, who uſe extream Rigour to Poor and unhappy Debtors, who have not wherewithal to pay: whereas would men have recourſe to the preſent Rule (of Forbearing and Forgiving one another) all theſe would be abhorred. Did we but conſider thoſe many Talents which we owe and cannot poſſibly ſatisfie: how could we deal
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171159:11"/>hardly with thoſe poor Debtors of ours that owe us a few Farthings. Did we weigh the Quality and Quantity of thoſe Tranſgreſſions which put us deep in <hi>Score;</hi> which if not blotted out, nothing but an Eternity of Miſery will attend us: How little Reaſon then have we, to purſue with Vehemency and Paſſion thoſe that have offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us? We are here commanded to Forbear and Forgive, as we hope to be Forgiven.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The laſt Vertue to be put on is <hi>Charitie. But above all put on Charitie.</hi> A Vertue this, more eſpecially required in the <hi>New-Man.</hi> Which makes the Apoſtle with a ſtrict Charge to renew his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, <hi>above all; praeter, ſuper, &amp; propter omnia,</hi> as 'tis diverſly rendred. — This, to follow the Metaphor of all Garments, is the moſt principal, 'tis as a Girdle which knits all the reſt together. As in Chriſtianity the <hi>New Creature</hi> is the All in All; ſo that which gives Life, Being and Splendor to that, is <hi>Charity:</hi> the firſt, the middle and the laſt. Here it perfects and compleats, elſewhere it leads the way to other Graces. As without it, <hi>The Tongues of Men and Angels</hi> are inſignificant; ſo they are unable ſufficiently to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Praiſe of it. In the Determination of the Schools, 'tis the very Life of Faith; in St. <hi>James</hi> his Divinity, an undeniable Argument of a living Faith; and by our Saviour noted as the great <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Badge of Diſcipleſhip. <hi>John</hi> 13.35. A Cardinal Grace, from whence as from a Fountain, moſt (if not all the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned) flow. For, where there is a right Chriſtian-Charity, there cannot but be <hi>Bowels of Mercies, Kindneſs, Humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering;</hi> the truly Charitable will be ready to <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear and Forgive.</hi> In brief, this is the Golden-rule, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-law; a ſure Friend that will follow us to another World, and render us acceptable in the Day of Judgment; that will remain when other Graces ſhall be done away. I ſhall ſpeak no more of this, but refer you to 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>Hitherto have I ſet before you the <hi>Old Man,</hi> together with its Spoils; — the principal parts of the <hi>New Creature,</hi> in reference to our duty each to other. I come now to propoſe ſome Arguments, which may prevail to the putting of it on; my Third Part:</p>
               <p>Nothing is ſo ſignificant as this: <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus, neither Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion availeth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but a New Creature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. And here in the firſt place, I think it not unfitting to urge you with an Argument from Nature. See how every Being puts off its Old, and calls for New Attire. The Fields by their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171159:12"/>Freſh Verdure, tell us plainly, that they are exchanging their Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and put on new Apparrel: and though <hi>Flora</hi> by the Stroak of Winter, as by Age ſullyed, had contracted Baldneſs and Deformity, within a few days ſhee'l ſhake off the Hagg, and grow young a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Behold the Trees, they have caſt off their old Fruit and Leaves are ſtripp'd naked, and all in order to new Apparrel. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lilies, they are committed to their Interment, which makes way to a ſplendid Reſurrection; they are withdrawn to their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring Rooms, and will ſhortly come forth with a glory by far fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing that of Kings. Nor is this leſs viſible in the Senſitive Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. The Birds of the Air part with their old <hi>Plumes,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear clad with a new Garb; each betraying, by his chirping Note, Youth and Vigour reaſſumed with the Seaſon. The Beaſts of the Field in like ſort, by their Briskneſs and Activity, proclaim to the World no ſmall Alteration. Thoſe who have a long time layen within their Cells buried, as in a deep Slumber, will now Begin to move and come to life again. Nay even the Serpent changes his Skin. As then the Piſmire teacheth the Sluggard Diligence, ſo ſhould the Creatures in the preſent Contemplation, powerfully inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Doctrine of the Text. All the Beings of the lower World, by the Benefit of the Heavenly Influences, and the unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Law of Nature, with the Year are renewed. What then can we do leſs, but abandon the <hi>Old Man,</hi> and make after the <hi>New Creature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. But if this Argument do not prevail, being fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for an <hi>Orator</hi> than a <hi>Divine;</hi> be pleaſed in the next place to conſider, how that the Church in her Service, at this
<note n="*" place="margin">New-years Day.</note> time more eſpecially does direct us hitherto. The Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the World was now, in Conformity to the Law, Circumciſed; which being a judicial Right, and by the people aboliſhed (as no ways advantageous) does notwithſtanding in its particular inſtance point hitherto. The Epiſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.8. directs us in the purſuit of ſuch a Faith as <hi>Abraham</hi> had, before he received the Seal of the Covenant. Now this Faith of the great Patriarch <hi>worked by Love,</hi> which runs parallel with the expreſſion of the Text. And then, though we are <hi>Gentiles,</hi> we have unqueſtionable Right to Filiation. We are Lawful and True Sons of the <hi>Circumciſed Jew,</hi> and ſhall without this Rite, have an undeniable Title to the Bleſſing. And the Collect teacheth us to pray <hi>For the true Circumciſion of the Spirit, the Mortification of our Hearts and Members from all Worldly Luſts,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171159:12"/>in order to Obedience and Conformity to Chriſts will in every thing;</hi> and what's that, but the <hi>New Creature?</hi> Religion does not oblige us to the cutting off the Fleſh of our Foreskin; but it neceſſarily requires that which by this Ceremony was ſhaddowed out and typified. We are not with the Phariſees to waſh and furbiſh the Outſide of the Diſh and Platter; but to have due regard to the cleaning of the Heart, the Fountain which makes our Thoughts, Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons either good or bad. The great Deſign of Chriſt in his Goſpel was, <hi>To redeem us from all Iniquity, and to purifie to himſelf a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar People, Zealous of good Works,</hi> Tit. 2.14. The moſt demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Argument of our Chriſtianity, is an Holy Change; and we may conclude, <hi>That we are Riſen with Chriſt, if with ardent Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction we ſeek thoſe things that are above; if our earthly Members are mortified: if we have put off the</hi> Old Man <hi>and put on the</hi> New, <hi>which after God, is created in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. An Argument drawn from the very Life and Eſſence of Chriſtianity. Without the <hi>New Creature,</hi> thoſe Prayers which we make are an abomination to the Lord, our Sabbaths and holy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances his Soul abhorreth, our whole Religion is vain. We may make broad our <hi>Phylacteries,</hi> Compaſs the Sea and Land to gain Proſelytes, make a fair Show in the World; but without the qualification of the Text, we can be no other than the Brats of the Wicked One, who is never more a Devil, than when he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the <hi>Form of a Cherubin.</hi> Men (ſaith the Prince of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation) <hi>Do not gather Grapes off Thorns, nor Figgs off Thiſtles.</hi> The Apoſtle lays down this as a Maxim, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>He that is in Chriſt is a new Creature;</hi> and further aſſures us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. <hi>That they that are Chriſt's, have Crucified the Fleſh with the Affections and Luſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee our Profeſſion requires no ſmall Change. The <hi>Old A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> muſt be renounced, that the <hi>New</hi> may be entertained; the Fleſh ſwallowed up by the Spirit; our Senſes muſt be forbidden to entertain Vanity, our Eyes dim-ſighted to irregular Glances, our Feet lame to the Path of Iniquity, our Palates dead to the draught of alluring Pleaſure, our Ears (according to the Preſident of the wiſe <hi>Ithacan</hi>) muſt be ſtop'd againſt the Mermaids Songs: Pleaſure muſt not entice, nor Profit muſt not entangle us; <hi>Delilah</hi> muſt not draw us down to <hi>Timnah,</hi> nor <hi>Lais</hi> put us upon a Journey to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. Achan's</hi> Wedge muſt not be the <hi>Diana,</hi> the Idol-Goddeſs of thy Heart. All Vice in general, and eſpecially the more leading, are inconſiſtent to Chriſtian Religion. Thou muſt take thy leave
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171159:13"/>of thine unſufferable Ambition: if thou deſireſt to be one of his Servants <hi>who hateth, beholdeth afar off, reſiſteth the Proud; but giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Grace unto the humble:</hi> thou muſt part with the ſweet Sin of Revenge; the God whom thou ſerveſt, challenges this as his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.18. <hi>Vengeance is mine, and I will repay it.</hi> If thou wilt be a devout Follower of the Great <hi>Galilean,</hi> thou muſt give a Bill of Divorce to Anger, Malice, Envy; — not be guilty of foul mouth'd Language; but obſerve the Rule of <hi>Yea, Yea, and Nay, Nay.</hi> Thou muſt <hi>turn the left Cheek to him that ſmites thee on the Right; part with thy Coat, to him that takes away thy Cloak.</hi> And what is a task of far greater difficulty, <hi>Love thine Enemies, Bleſs them that Curſe thee, do good to them that hate thee, pray for them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully uſe and perſecute thee.</hi> Mat. 5.44. <hi>Forgive not only ſeven, but ſeventy times ſeven Treſpaſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe I take not to be Counſels, <hi>i. e.</hi> Doctrines delivered by way of Advice to the Sons of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> thoſe who propoſe to themſelves the <hi>Right Hand, and the Left Hand of Chriſt in his Kingdom,</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Supremacy in Heaven, as the Patriots of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church would perſwade us; but formal Precepts, to which in their right ſenſe all Chriſtians are obliged. Is it not the great Deſign of Chriſt's Sermon on the Mount, and his others, to refine and exalt his Followers, not only above the Dregs, but the ſtricteſt ſect among Mankind; being required to live above the <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane,</hi> and upon the greateſt penalty to exceed the <hi>Scribe and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee in Righteouſneſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are the Commands of our General who, not (as the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees) obliges our Backs to theſe heavy Burthens, which he would not touch himſelf; but in this like <hi>Ceſar,</hi> who was never obſerved to bid his Souldiers <hi>Go,</hi> but <hi>Come.</hi> In his Practice he leads us the way, and frequently propoſes his Example for a Pattern for our Imitation. — <hi>Be ye Perfect as I am Perfect, — Holy as I am Holy, — Learn of me.</hi> Trace his Life, and ſee how eminently thoſe Vertues which he requires of us, ſhine forth in him: <hi>v. g. His Bowels of Mercy, his Meekneſs, Humbleneſs, Long-ſuffering.</hi> Now he <hi>ſerves,</hi> to teach his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples Condeſcention, anon he <hi>waſhes their Feet,</hi> thereby reading them a lively Lecture of their Comportment eath to other. — He refuſes to be made King; — He takes no notice of the many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilings he met withal; in his Sufferings, he expreſſes unparallel Patience; <hi>being led as a Sheep to the Slaughter, and as a Lamb dumb before his Shearers, opened he not his Mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:171159:13"/>
               <p>Let us for our Encouragement ſee how after this Copy the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Converts did write; upon their admiſſion we ſhall diſcover them far different from what they were (like <hi>Abraham</hi> in his Journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Meſopotamia</hi>) Taking leave of their Country and kindred, and Fathers Houſe; or as the Kings Daughter in the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 45.10. <hi>Forgetting her own People and her Fathers Houſe.</hi> Parting with all their Carnal Affections.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Matthew</hi> upon his Call does quit his <hi>Office;</hi> abhorring no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than his former Trade of living. A Diſciple muſt not be a <hi>Publicane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zaccheus</hi> is no ſooner called down from the Sycamore-tree, to be engrafted in the true Vine; no ſooner affected with Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but he publiſheth it by an Alteration wonderfull; he no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er receives Chriſt within his Houſe, but he reſigned the full Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Heart: he teſtifies his Repentance by that Reſtitution which he makes (the ſureſt marke of unfeigned Contrition in the preſent Caſe:) the Sincerity of his Faith, by the meaſure of his Charity: — <hi>Lord the half of my Goods I give to the Poor; and if I have taken any thing from any man by falſe Accuſation, I reſtore him four-fold,</hi> Luke 19.8. See farther how the <hi>New Creature</hi> ſhines forth in <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> after her Converſion; we have great reaſon to ſuppoſe the former part of her life notoriouſly wicked, from that Helliſh Crew which quartered with her: For if <hi>one ſingle Devil</hi> cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate no ſmall Extravagancie where he is: what wickedneſs ſhall not <hi>ſeven</hi> Devils united practiſe? Beſide, ſhe is deſcribed to be a <hi>Sinner, Luke</hi> 7.37. <hi>i. e.</hi> not as ſome in favour (as they think) to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity and its preſent Proſelyte, upon a great miſtake have conſtrued <hi>an ordinary Sinner:</hi> but 'tis with the unanimous conſent of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty agreed on, that the expreſſion denotes her one <hi>lewd</hi> and <hi>unclean;</hi> and if not actually ſuch, yet little leſs than a <hi>Proſtitute.</hi> And ſo no ſooner are the Devils driven out, but that the Fleſh is ſubdued, and ſhe becomes quite another thing; ſhe is a conſtant Attender on our Saviour: whilſt her Siſter is buſied about the <hi>Cares of the World,</hi> She has her Eye on the grand Concern, the <hi>one thing neceſſary.</hi> She provides <hi>a Box of Oyntment</hi> coſtly and odoriferous, againſt his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral: <hi>waſhes his Feet with her Tears, and wipes them with the Hairs of her Head:</hi> She laments him Crucified, is the firſt Woman upon Record, who prevented the <hi>Dawning of the day,</hi> to enquire after his Reſurrection. Though the Apoſtles forſake him and fly, ſhe ſcorns to flinch; is the firſt Preacher of the Reſurrection, and, as one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171159:14"/>calls her, <hi>Apoſtolorum Apoſtola,</hi> the Doctreſs of the Apoſtles. If after all this we call to mind the Carriage of the <hi>Protomartyr,</hi> we have a new motive to duty. His Converſation was like his <hi>Countenance,</hi> of which St. <hi>Luke</hi> Records, <hi>That it did ſhine like an Angel,</hi> Acts 6. <hi>ult.</hi> He has nothing of the <hi>Old Man</hi> in him; he requires the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Cruelty and Envy of his Enemies, with an high Act of Charity and Zeal; he is praying for them, while they are ſtoning him: when they are putting an end to his Mortal Life, he Petitions the Throne of Grace for their Forgiveneſs, and conſequently their Converſion: And ſome of his Perſecutors reap'd the benefit of his Devotions, It being a received Opinion, <hi>Eccleſia non habuiſſet Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum niſi oraſſet Stephanus;</hi> God anſwering his Prayer by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> which affords us another Inſtance:</p>
               <p>What he was before his Converſion, is ſo plain from his own and St. <hi>Lukes</hi> account, as that none can be ignorant of it. <hi>He conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to</hi> S. Stephens <hi>Death; he breathed out Threatnings and Slaughter againſt the Diſciples of the Lord; to effect which, he procured of the High-Prieſt a Commiſſion:</hi> ſome he Impriſoned, others he perſecuted to ſtrange Cities. One ſufficiently wicked and bloody both in his Intentions and Actions.</p>
               <p>But no ſooner is he ſmitten, and hears a <hi>Voice,</hi> but that he becomes quite another Creature; he trembling and aſtoniſhing ſaid, <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> Acts 9.6. The Lion is changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lamb; the bold Perſecutor relents; thoſe very hands which lately were the Inſtruments of the <hi>Slaughter,</hi> are now (like thoſe of <hi>Moſes</hi>) lifted up to God for the <hi>Preſervation of the Saints:</hi> his Tongue forgetting to <hi>Blaſpheme,</hi> knows no other Language but that of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan:</hi> his ſtubborn Knees are Pliant, bending in their Devotion, as their proper poſture: <hi>Behold he prayeth! Acts</hi> 9.11. He is a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Veſſel to bear God's Name before the Gentiles and Kings, and Children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> he refuſes no Labours or Difficulties: with boldneſs he Preaches the Goſpel before the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Rulers;</hi> for the Teſtimony whereof, he is as willing to ſacrifice his deareſt Blood, as before he thirſted to take it from others. The Deſtroyer at length is become the Builder, with no ſmall advantage to the Church, repairing thoſe Breaches which he in times paſt made. So he tells us, <hi>He would gladly ſpend and be ſpent: he is ready not only to be bound, but alſo to ſuffer for the Name of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> And come what will come, he is reſolved <hi>to preach that Faith which once he did deſtroy.</hi> He is all Bowels and Love, who before was all Hatred and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171159:14"/>Malice. 'Tis this that brings him from one part of the World to the other; that puts him upon writing his Epiſtles; and to his great loſs, to deſire a longer continuance in this miſerable World; yea ſo high and towering is the Charity of this great Doctor, as that he gives us an Inſtance which hath not a ſecond: <hi>He could wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf accurſed from Chriſt for his Brethren and Kinſmens ſake,</hi> Rom. 9.3.</p>
               <p>Nor was the <hi>New Creature</hi> the Badge of Chriſtianity in its Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy only;
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apol.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Senat. Rom.</hi>
                  </note> upon examination we ſhall find it to be the <hi>Shibboleth</hi> in after-Ages: for thus <hi>Juſtin</hi> Martyr tells us, <hi>That the Woman who formerly was incontinent, upon her Converſion became Chaſt and Sober. — And he farther relates, how that</hi> Ptolomeus <hi>profeſſing himſelf a Chriſtian, by</hi> Urbitius <hi>being condemned:</hi> Lucius <hi>another Chriſtian,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>openly upbraids the Governour with the unjuſtneſs of the Sentence, being paſſed on a Man of unblameable Converſation. What's the reaſon that he is thus puniſhed who is no Adulterer, Fornicator, Murtherer, Thief, Extortioner?</hi> — And in his ſecond
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nin.</hi>
                  </note> Apology, he had this paſſage, <hi>We who formerly rejoyced in Adulteries, now greedily embrace Chaſtity: we who addicted our ſelves to Magical Arts, now wholly devote our ſelves to God: we who Idolized Riches and Worldly ſubſtance, now have all things in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, diſtributing to the Indigent: we who did burn with mutual Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and Envy, now are loving, and pray for our Enemies.</hi> —</p>
               <p>In like ſort <hi>Tertullian</hi> urges the Teſtimony of an Enemy,
<note place="margin">Apol.</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Pliny</hi> the ſecond who in an Epiſtle to <hi>Trajan,</hi> has this Paſſage: that the Chriſtians, for ought he could perceive, beſide their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy in refuſing to ſacrifice to the Emperor, had nothing in their Sacred Rites, but that they were wont to meet before day to ſing Praiſes to Chriſt and God: forbidding Murder, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Deceit, and other Wickedneſs; — And further does aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, that the Change of the Primitive Chriſtians was ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently viſible, as that their very Enemies could not chuſe but confeſs them to be good Men; they had no fault to lay to their Charge but this, that thy were Chriſtians. — Whereas in truth this (as another hath obſerved) was the Fountain of all their Vertues.
<note place="margin">Lactantius.</note> And when ſome by reaſon of their <hi>Night-Aſſemblies,</hi> took occaſion to accuſe them, as carrying on Deſigns of Rebellion, Murther, Thievery, Uncleanneſs: — He larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purges them from theſe, aſſerting them to be the <hi>Pillars of their Age;</hi> that they lived up to the great Principle of their Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171159:15"/>
                     <hi>not to wiſh, do, think, or ſpeak evil of any.</hi> — That it was not out of want either of Opportunity or power, that they did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge themſelves upon their Enemies; only their Religion does reſtrain them.— He dares their Adverſaries to find out among them a Traytor, Robber, Murtherer, any notoriouſly wicked. — They are altogether what ſingle, united what divided; they hurt none, they grieve none; of a ſober, chaſt, and Godly Carriage; the only innocent perſons. — Their Religion has exalted them to an higher Eminency than ever the moſt refined among the Heathens could pretend to. — <hi>Democritus</hi> had no other way, but to pull out his Eyes, that he might not behold Vanity; whereas the Devout <hi>Chriſtian</hi> can look on a Beauty without Luſting after her. The <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of the ſtricteſt Sect and greateſt Note, have betrayed <hi>Pride, Vain-glory, Cowardiſe, Baſeneſs;</hi> of which he gives many Examples; but the Chriſtians are guilty of none of theſe. —</q>
               </p>
               <p>In this Argument, as the moſt irrefragable; the Primitive Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters think that they have good reaſon to triumph over their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen con. Celſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 85.</note> One tells his Adverſary (no mean Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher as well as Heretick) <hi>That the Doctrine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did Convert the moſt Vitious Perſons from their former Debaucheries, to the practice of Temperance and all other Vertues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I conclude this with that Elegant Paſſage of <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Fal. Sap. c.</hi> 26.</note> the power of Philoſophy is but impotence in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon to that of true Religion; of the former, Nature gets the upper hand; ſo that the Philoſopher after all his Documents, (like the Dog) returns to his Vomit. This Phyſick is not efficacious to a perfect Cure, but he falls of courſe into a Relapſe; whereas the force of Chriſtian Religion is wonderful; of which there are every day's Examples: whereupon he makes this Challenge, <hi>Bring me the Man that is Angry, Ill-natur'd, Stubborn; by a Lecture from Chriſtianity I'le make him as gentle as a Lamb. Bring me the Man that is pinching and Covetous; I'le make him truly Liberal, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting with both his Hands. Bring the Man that is afraid of Pain and Death: I'le make him ſo truly Valiant, that he ſhall not be moved at the Fire and Faggot; he ſhall deſpiſe even the Bull of</hi> Phalaris. <hi>Bring me the Man that is incontinent and gluttonous: I'le make him chaſt and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Bring me the Man that is cruel and blood-thirſty: I'le make him merciful. Bring me an Extortioner, or any other ſinner: and in a ſhort
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171159:15"/>time, I'le make the ſame perſon juſt and innocent.</hi> The Waſhing or Regeneration purifies <hi>from all Malice;</hi> and the force of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſuch, <hi>as that it puts to flight the Old Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if Chriſtian Religion heretofore wrought in the manners of Men ſo heavenly a Change, how much does it concern us who profeſs the ſame, to give the World a Teſtimony by the like De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that we are not <hi>Whited Sepulchres, as founding Braſs, and tinkling Cymbals:</hi> Chriſtians, not only in Show, but in Truth?</p>
               <p>This Argument I have handled more largely, becauſe I look on it as the moſt genuine, and ſubſtantial of the Text. I paſs for your Encouragement to others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. The living in the practice of the aforeſaid Duties ſhall beſpeak us truly <hi>gentile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have always been of opinion, that true Gentility carrieth in it ſomewhat more than ordinary. A generous Stream of Vertuous and Heroick Qualities <hi>circle</hi> in noble Veins. <hi>The Son of</hi> Hector <hi>betrays Courage in his Cradle;</hi> by the Benefit whereof, upon the Top of the Tower o're which he is to be thrown, he can at once look his Enemies and Death in the Face. Such as are nobly deſcended, can (like the Off-ſpring of the Eagle) behold things ſplendid as their proper Object, which would <hi>dazle</hi> the Eyes of the <hi>Dunghil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breed.</hi> Whereupon 'tis obvious to obſerve, that even Afflictions cannot alter their Nature; though oppreſſed, they will not be o'recome; though under ſtraights, they betray ſtill a generous Soul: they ſcorne Actions dirty and Sordid. — To prey upon Flies, to pilfer and undoe them that are below them; in their Carriage full of Courteſie. Whereas thoſe of the <hi>Muſhrom Production,</hi> betray low and ignoble Spirits, and (like that Creature in the Fable) by a ſordid Port, plainly diſcover themſelves under the <hi>Lion's Skin. Julius Capitolinus</hi> tells, that from the Vitious, Dirty, and Sordid Behaviour of <hi>Commodus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Vit. Ant. natum Com. gladiatorem in principem.</note> 'twas generally conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that he was not the Son of <hi>Antoninus,</hi> but of ſome Ruffian <hi>Hector.</hi> — There was no Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, no Hogherd, no Villain like him. He that lives not up to the principles of Generoſity and Proweſs, does plainly argue himſelf to degenerate; is the diſgrace of his Family, and gives a Blot to his Eſcutcheon.</p>
               <p>Now will any affirm, that this is gentile, to be o'rewhelmed with <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Cruelty?</hi> to take pleaſure in the Ruine of our Fellow-Creatures?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171159:16"/>Is it an Act of Fortitude (like <hi>Saul</hi> among the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites</hi>) to cruſh thoſe that are not able to reſiſt us? Is it an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a large Soul (like the Dog in the Manger) to bite and bark; and prohibite that to others, which to our ſelves is both uſeleſs and cumberſome?</p>
               <p>The King of Beaſts ſpares the Proſtrate, will not exerciſe his Strength where he meets with no oppoſition. To deſtroy a weak, punie and beggarly Enemy, is not a Victory but Diſparagement. We are not born for our ſelves alone; our Country, Kindred and Fellow-deniſons claim a ſhare. This ſingle Inducement made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Heathens to prefer the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> before their <hi>Private Intereſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Believe it Sirs, we ſhall appear highly gentile by Acts of <hi>Love, Mercy, and Meekneſs;</hi> by giving (as the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors were wont upon great Solemnities) <hi>largeſſes to others; by relieving and maintaining the Poor; by pleading the Cauſe of the Fatherleſs and Widdow; by furthering the good of others, and doing what Service we can in our own Generation.</hi> Hither <hi>Nature</hi> does direct us (if the great Philoſopher were not miſtaken) every Being runs out of his way, for the Preſervation of the Univerſe. — And if we have recourſe to the Sun, Moon and Stars, the Hoſt of Heaven: Lo, they Dart their <hi>Rays,</hi> and vouchſafe their Influencies to all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Exception; to the loweſt as well as higheſt, to the worſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually with the beſt of Creatures. If we look above the Heavens, and conſider the Actions of the <hi>Supreme;</hi> he has no ſmall care of the meaneſt Creatures; he is full of <hi>Bowels, Patience, Long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> he proſecutes his Enemies with unparallel'd acts of <hi>Love;</hi> and what higher Inducement can be deſired? In this chiefly we ſhall be like him; beſpeak our ſelves nobly deſcended; and if not from ſome ancient Family, and great Houſe; yet from the <hi>moſt glorious King and Empirean Palace;</hi> and not only in the ſenſe of <hi>Aratus,</hi> but a more approved, even that of our Saviour: we ſhall declare our ſelves his <hi>Off-ſpring, Mat.</hi> 5.44. — <hi>That ye may be the Children of your Father which is in Heaven: for he maketh his Sun to riſe on the Evil, and on the Good; and ſendeth Rain on the Juſt and on the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. Such Acts as theſe; <hi>as they beſpeak us truly gentile, ſo are they highly obliging.</hi> The Sun by its warmth and gentle Rays, gains from the Traveller that Coat which the bluſtering Wind faſtened cloſer to him. Much more is to be accompliſhed by Kindneſs,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171159:16"/>than by all the methods of Severity. 'Tis confeſſed, Tyrants may compell and make their Vaſſals pliant; by extream rigour I may bring many to my beck, but I cannot keep them there. This is a Method to treat a Slave withal, one who has ſhaken off all Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. This may render thee terrible; but at the ſame time thou ſhalt not be without daily Fears and Trepidations. Like the brute beaſts, they will be ſerviceable no longer than they are under the Yoak; being releaſed they'l rebell, and upon the firſt occaſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thy greateſt Enemies. Whereupon we find the ſevereſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants to have lived moſt miſerable lives; their own fears at leaſt equal if not greater than thoſe of their Slaves; they fancy Poyſon mixed with their Meat and Drink; they ſleep not without Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; and as we read of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> in <hi>Cicero:</hi> they chuſe rather to <hi>ſinge</hi> their <hi>Beards,</hi> than truſt a <hi>Barber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas the Cords of Love are eaſie, pleaſant and ſtrong. Men take delight to be caught in theſe, and to be led where you pleaſe. The beſt allowable and moſt laſting <hi>Philtre</hi> to command the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men, is a ſweet and vertuous Carriage: be kind and obliging to thoſe that are round about thee; and their good Wiſhes, Preſents and Services are at thy Devotion. 'Twas by ſuch Acts as theſe, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> arrived to that height he did; he was always kind and liberal to his Souldiers, ſharing with them in all Dangers and Straights; upon every occaſion dividing among them the Spoils of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and ſometimes the Treaſure even of <hi>Rome.</hi> He knocked off the Shackles which thoſe before him had put on; eaſing many of their ſevere Impoſitions. In his Carriage toward his Enemies, full of Pitty and Forgiveneſs; the former made his Troops more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous every day than other; the latter ſtill leſſen'd his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: all made way to the <hi>Motto</hi> of <hi>veni, vidi, vici:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Decad.</hi> 1. <hi>Lib.</hi> 5.</note> Intitled him to a univerſal Conqueſt. 'Tis a brave Paſſage which the Hiſtorian <hi>Livie</hi> has obſerved of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millus</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> General, when he ſate before the Town of the <hi>Faliſci,</hi> cloſely beſieging it; a certain <hi>Pedagogue,</hi> to whom was committed the Care and Management of the chief Youth of the Place; comes to the Beſieger, brings with him his Schollars; and withal tells him, that they were the beloved Sons of his Enemies within; and therefore if he pleaſed to take them, the City upon their account, would be forced to ſurrender ſuddainly: the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to the preſent end muſt be acknowledged effectual; but they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171159:17"/>are too baſe for the Noble <hi>Roman</hi> to ſtoop unto; whereupon in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the Councellor and Advice, he commands the Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado-Traytor to be ſtripp'd naked, and each Youth with a Rod in his hand to whip the treacherous Villain back again into the Town; thereby declaring to his Enemies, that he ſcorned Victory by ſo baſe a means.</p>
               <p>Now ſee the event: this high Paſſage took ſo mightily with thoſe within, as that they preſently yielded up the City and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>Camillus;</hi> making it the matter of their Choice to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Government of ſo brave a Man. <hi>His Love makes way where his Sword cannot; and when Arms are ineffectual, Mercy gains the Town.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. This gets us Repute among our Enemies; we are taught that 'tis the Glory of a Man to paſs by an Offence. The Noble Philoſopher and Emperour who lived (if any) ſutable to his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<note place="margin">Capitolin. in Vita</note> and found the benefit of it himſelf; having gained upon the Affections of all (<hi>unicè amabant</hi> ſaith the Hiſtorian) <hi>Tells us that Love and Meekneſs are things unconquerable: for how ſhall even the moſt fierce and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous be able to hold on againſt thee, if thou ſhalt ſtill continue meek and loving to him? And even at that time when he ſhall do thee wrong, thou ſhalt be well diſpoſed toward him?</hi> And what's this, but the very Doctrine of the Scripture, which directs us to the Practice of <hi>Vertue and Goodneſs,</hi> as the ſureſt Expedient to o'recome Evil. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20. <hi>If thine Enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirſt, give him Drink: for in ſo doing, thou ſhalt heap Coals of Fire on his</hi> Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. Such Acts as theſe ſhall exalt thee in the World. Thou canſt not propoſe to thy ſelf a better Fortreſs to thy Caſtle; 'twill ſet it above, or at leaſt make it ſufficient Proof againſt all Storms; whilſt the Habitation of the Proud is Slippery. The <hi>Cedar</hi> dwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles into a <hi>Shrub;</hi> his Greatneſs ends in Shame; <hi>ſuddenly do they periſh, and come to a fearful end.</hi> That man is the <hi>Glory of his Age,</hi> in whom <hi>Mercy and Truth meet together. Righteouſneſs and Peace</hi> go hand in hand;
<note place="margin">Sueton. in Tito.</note> and upon a much better account than that <hi>Emperour to whom 'twas given,</hi> deſerve the Title of <hi>Amor &amp; Deliciae humanae generis,</hi> the <hi>Darling and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of Mankind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis obſervable, when the Prophet deſcribeth the Man that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lord; he chuſeth to do it by thoſe Vertues which he does
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171159:17"/>exert towards Man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112. <hi>He is Gracious and full of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, Righteous, v.</hi> 4. <hi>he is one that lendeth; v.</hi> 5. <hi>he is known by his Acts of Charity; he diſperſeth and giveth to the Poor.</hi>— Now for your Encouragement be pleaſed to add to theſe former, one Obſervation more, <hi>viz.</hi> how many and great Bleſſings wait on this man. 1. <hi>His Seed ſhall be mighty upon Earth.</hi> 2. <hi>Wealth and Riches ſhall be in his Houſe, and his Righteouſneſs endureth for ever.</hi> 3. <hi>To him there ariſeth Light in Darkneſs.</hi> 4. <hi>He ſhall not be moved for ever, but had in everlaſting Remembrance.</hi> 5. <hi>He ſhall not be afraid of Evil Tidings, his Heart is eſtabliſhed.</hi> 6. <hi>He ſhall ſee his deſire upon his Enemies; and to their no ſmall grief, his Houſe ſhall be exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Honour.</hi> —</p>
               <p>Are there, or can there be greater temporal Bleſſings than theſe, the beloved Objects of all? What would the Proud man give for Honour? The Angry, Envious and Malicious, that they might have their purpoſe upon their Enemies? But theſe by Their <hi>Mediums</hi> are not to be obtained. The Devil, though he be very prodigal in his <hi>Promiſes,</hi> is very ſparing in his <hi>Performance;</hi> he does deceive the Senſes, and delude the Expectations of his <hi>Servants. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World, and the Glory of them,</hi> in the concluſion prove <hi>Golden Mountains, Chimaera's.</hi> The Sinner inſtead of Honour meets with Diſgrace; when he thinks he has obtained his purpoſe, he claſps a <hi>Shaddow;</hi> has no other Fruit of all his <hi>Toil,</hi> but what the Apoſtle has noted, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>ult. Death.</hi> Whereas, if the Word of God be true, the forementioned Bleſſings ſhall attend the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man:</hi> Thoſe that live in the Practice of theſe Vertues ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted in the World like ſo many <hi>Cities upon Hills,</hi> for as the ſame Prophet has elſewhere noted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.6. <hi>'Tis Righteouſneſs that makes men ſhine as the Light, and juſt Dealing as the Noon-day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 8. <hi>This ſhall entitle us to the Prayers and Services of thoſe that are round about us.</hi> The <hi>Centurion</hi> though a <hi>Gentile,</hi> by his Acts of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Munificence, had ſo endeared the <hi>Jews</hi> unto him, as that upon every occaſion they are his humble Servants, <hi>Luke</hi> 7. one of his Attendants is ſick, and they make to the Phyſician, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that he would heal him, being the Servant of a Worthy Man, <hi>who loved their Nation, and built them a Synagogue.</hi> Where there is any Humanity our Love and Kindneſs will be requited: The Poor at our Doors which we have <hi>fed</hi> and <hi>clad,</hi> will be our Solicitors to the Throne of Grace. The Widdow and Fatherleſs whoſe Cauſe we have pleaded.— Thoſe Friends whom we have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171159:18"/>reconciled— forborn:— been any ways beneficial to; will be the <hi>Heralds</hi> of our Praiſe, and ſtudy occaſions to do us good. And who knows how beneficial the Prayers and Services of ſuch may be to us? God may gratifie them in their Requeſts for us, when we cannot prevail for our ſelves: For 'twas the <hi>Centurions Faith,</hi> that induced our Saviour to heal his Servant; <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.13. And the Faith of others is recorded the occaſion of the Cure of the <hi>Paralytical, Mat.</hi> 9.2. Thus alſo <hi>Potipher</hi> fares the better for <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.5. And when we reſign our Tabernacles to Duſt, our Funerals ſhall be like that of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> attended with the <hi>Lamentations of Devout Men:</hi> or, as we read of <hi>Dorcas, Acts</hi> 9.36.39. Thoſe whom ſhe relieved appeared in her Livery, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed abroad her Charity, and dropt Tears upon her Herſe. The like <hi>Threnodies</hi> we have often heard. — <hi>Alas he was a good Man! beneficial and advantageous in his Generation; the Fatherleſs, the Poor, the Oppreſſed, the Widdow, the Labourer — will find him wanting: It had been happy for us had he continued longer here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Such Acts as theſe ſhall perfume thy Grave, and perpetuate thy Memory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 9. An happy Paſſage out of this World, is the main end of our Life; our laſt Enemy is terrible, and the Dominions of Darkneſs are full of <hi>ſtench:</hi> wherefore our greateſt Endeavour ſhould be to take away the ſting of the one, and ſweeten the other. To theſe ends, ſome <hi>put far from them the Evil Day.</hi> The <hi>Epicure</hi> uſes the Charm of a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> — And the rich man ſpares no Coſt in the preſervatives which either Art or Nature can afford: whereas there is no ſuch Expedient as the living in the diſcharge of the aforeſaid Vertues. This will make the ſtroak of Death plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and render thy Sepulchre (like that of the <hi>Arimathean</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for our Saviour) full of <hi>Spices:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">St. Chryſoſt.</note> For thus one of the Ancients tells us, <hi>The Righteous Man, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth Death a coming, which he always looked on as preſent, is not ſurpriſed or troubled as other Men, entertains it not as an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but as a Friend.</hi> If upon thy Summons thou canſt ſay with <hi>Hezekiah; Lord, I have walked before thee in Truth, and with a perfect Heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight,</hi> Iſa. 38.3. Thou haſt reaſon to conclude with <hi>David, I will lay me down in Peace and take my reſt; — wherefore my Heart was glad, my Glory rejoyced, my Fleſh ſhall alſo reſt in Hope.</hi> I have, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my abilitie, done good in my Generation; I have exerciſed my Bowels and Love upon occaſion: and where I have been defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171159:18"/>I have and do beg with Humility and Contrition, Pardon: I have a good Conſcience, and a Gracious God; I truſt in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and hope for Mercy in the time of need. And foraſmuch as Men cannot be immortal in their <hi>Perſons</hi> here, they covet to be ſo in their <hi>Memories:</hi> which they are willing to purchaſe at any rate. Whereupon one <hi>leaps</hi> into the Mouth of <hi>Aetna,</hi> that he might be talk'd of in after-Ages. Another ſets the famous Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi> on Fire, thereby to raiſe him an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Pile. 'Twas this that drove the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> in his diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and dangerous Attempts over the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Mountains, that he might be the <hi>Subject of future Diſcourſe.</hi> Upon this account great men build them deſolate Places, coſtly Vaults and Monuments—but all theſe bear no Proportion to the preſent Expedient, Epitaphs within a while will not be <hi>legible;</hi> and the moſt durable Monuments will moulder into Duſt; whereas Vertue and Grace are perpetual. Do Good in thy Generation, and thou ſhalt leave living Monuments of thy Praiſe behind. — <hi>If thou doſt well men will ſpeak good of thee:</hi> — and elſewhere, <hi>the Righteous ſhall be had in Everlaſting Remembrance.</hi> Men will tell it their Children, they theirs, and ſo by Tradition ſhall it be delivered from Age to Age. The Love of <hi>Mary,</hi> the good Works of <hi>Dorcas,</hi> the Charity of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> ſhall be coequal with the World.</p>
               <p>But if there ſhould be no Records of thy Acts of Love and Mercy here below, know for thy Encouragement, that the great God of Heaven keeps a <hi>Regiſter, and all theſe are noted in his Book,</hi> before whoſe Tribunal thou muſt ſhortly appear. If then thou expecteſt <hi>Bowels, Meekneſs, Forgiveneſs, Mercy,</hi> be willing to ſhew it to thy Brethren now; this is Religion, this the new Creature.</p>
               <p>In order to the putting on of which, before I proceed to the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication I ſhall propoſe one Expedient, which is not ſo properly Mine as <hi>Solomon</hi>'s, viz. <hi>to diſcarde the Tale-bearer, then all Strife ſhall ceaſe,</hi> Prov. 26.20.</p>
               <p>There are a ſort of People far more obnoxious than the Frogs of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> who to our no ſmall Diſturbance croak in moſt of our Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, a ſort which the Law has mark'd and ranked with murderers, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.16. Which the Wiſe man has more than once warned us of, Prov. 11.13. and 18.8. when the Prophet gives a Catalogue of the crying Sins of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he ſpecifies this in the firſt Place, <hi>in thee are men that carry Tales to ſhed Blood.</hi> Ezek. 22.9.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:171159:19"/>
               <p>A Smooth-tongu'd Generation to the Life, by the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> upon his woful Experience deſcribed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22. <hi>The Words of his Mouth were ſofter than Butter, having War in his Heart; his Words were ſmoother than Oyl, and yet be they very Swords.</hi> The beſt reſemblance that I can make of them, is to <hi>Pedlars,</hi> who are well inſtructed in the Art of Canting, of magnifying their Ware; who come to us full loaden, carry from, and bring ſomewhat to us, and in concluſion impoſe upon us.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Janſenius.</hi>
                  </note> A fraudulent, deceitful, double-tongu'd, yea triple-tongu'd Paraſite, as he is diverſly ſet out; one who will cut your Throat with a Feather; and, like the Crocodile, when he deſigns Deſtruction, <hi>Weeps;</hi> the Devil's Seed-man of his Tares; <hi>Judas</hi> revived: For 'tis generally agreed on, that the 55. <hi>Pſal.</hi> wherein <hi>David</hi> ſets the Flatterers of his days out, Is Typical and Prophetical of this Traytor; who with <hi>Hail Maſter,</hi> and the <hi>Complement of a Kiſs:</hi> will for far leſs than the ſumm of <hi>thirty pieces,</hi> deliver his <hi>deareſt Friend</hi> into the Hands of his Enemies.</p>
               <p>'Tis not to be conceived what miſchief is done in the World by this kind of Cattle; of all Enemies the worſt; the grand Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of our Quiet. No Wounds, no Stabbs like his; he ſtrikes when we do not imagine, but lie moſt open to his Stroak. What he hears at one Houſe, he relates to the next, but with Addition, which carries Gun-pouder in it; and if he can meet with no Tale, he has a pregnant Fancy, and can invent as many as he liſts None can boaſt of ſo univerſal a Conqueſt as this <hi>wheedling Sycophant;</hi> when he pleaſes, he can make Diſturbance in greater, as well as leſſer Societies; he can divide Houſes, Pariſhes, Kingdoms, not only from each other, but among themſelves; at Will, break off all Leagues, diſturb Friendſhip and Peace; ſet the Father againſt the Son, and the Son againſt the Father; the Daughter againſt the Mother; the Brother againſt the Brother.— And, when the Bill of <hi>Moſes</hi> cannot, effectually divide thoſe who are one Fleſh.</p>
               <p>Let us ſee the miſchief in a few Examples: <hi>Sampſon</hi> the great terrour of his Enemies, who with the Jaw-bone of an Aſs (that which firſt came to hand) ſlew as many of his Enemies as he pleaſed; who carried away the Gates of the City on his Shoulders, ſtill returned Conqueror: — falls at laſt by Treachery. His Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome-Friend betrays him into the Hands of the Philiſtines; and by this, as the only means, the great Champion of <hi>Iſrael</hi> became the Object of their Scorn and Deriſion.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:171159:19"/>
               <p>Of thoſe twenty three Wounds which <hi>Caeſar</hi> received in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, there was none which went ſo near his Heart, as that of his Son. <hi>Many Deaths in one!</hi> to fall by his Son, who ought to have died for him! to fall by an Inſtrument of his own making!</p>
               <p>Not much unlike to this, is the Caſe of <hi>David. The Man after God's own Heart</hi> was not free from theſe; he had many Enemies, 'tis true; but <hi>none ſo pernicious, as thoſe of his own Houſe:</hi> as yet a Shepherd, he lays the Lion and the Bear proſtrate, with no other Weapon but a <hi>Sling,</hi> and a <hi>few Stones.</hi> The Man of <hi>Gath</hi> as an eaſie <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim</hi> falls before him. <hi>Saul</hi> with all his malicious Contrivances is not able to do him hurt; but when his Son ſhall rebell, and his chief Councellor revolt; his Spirits begin to ſink; a <hi>fluctus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumanus, a tenth wave this,</hi> which threatens inevitable Deſtruction, uſhers in a deluge of Tears, makes his Couch to ſwim, and his Bed to overflow. Hear him in his own Expreſſion: <hi>It is not an open Enemy that hath done me this Diſhonour: for then I could have born it; neither was it mine Adverſary that did magnifie himſelf againſt me: for then peradventure I ſhould have hid my ſelf from him: but it was even thou my Companion, my Guide, and my familiar Friend; We took ſweet Counſel together, and walked in the Houſe of God as Friends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to add one Inſtance more; we are told that <hi>Troy</hi> ſtood it out valiantly againſt ten years Siege; the great Councellors and Captains of <hi>Greece,</hi> with all their Attempts could prevail nothing; till at laſt they make Uſe of a wheedling Flatterer: — who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of Love and Service does effect their Ruine: delivers them over unto the Sword, and turns their City into a Field.</p>
               <p>They are ſuch Creatures as theſe, that threaten our <hi>Troys;</hi> the Inſtruments that diſturb our Peace and Quiet: If we enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them, they will give us fair words; but theſe ſooner or later, <hi>will go into the Bowels of the Belly,</hi> if the Doctrine of the wiſe man be true <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.8. But on the contrary, the diſcountenancing, the removing of them, by the Bleſſing of God, will be the Means of putting off the Wolf, and putting on the <hi>Man,</hi> yea the <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> In ſo doing, we ſhall conſult our own Happineſs, be in the right Path to true Love, and beſpeak our ſelves what our Profeſſion requires us. To this effect is the Doctrine of the wiſeſt of Men <hi>(loc. cit.) Where there is no Wood the Fire goeth out: So where there is no
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171159:20"/>Tale-bearer, the Strife ceaſeth.</hi> I ſhall cloſe this, with that excellent Paſſage of the Son of <hi>Syrack, Ecclus.</hi> 28.13. <hi>&amp;c. Abhor the Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and double-tongu'd:</hi> for ſuch have <hi>deſtroyed many that were at Peace. the Double-tongue has diſquieted many,</hi> and driven them from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Nation; <hi>ſtrong Cities hath it broken down,</hi> and o'rethrown the <hi>Houſes of great Men:</hi> the Strength of the People hath it brought <hi>down, and been</hi> the decay of mighty Nations. The Double-tongue hath <hi>caſt out</hi> many Vertuous Women, and robbed them of their Labours. <hi>Who ſo hearkeneth</hi> unto it, ſhall never find reſt, and never dwell quietly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>ANd now I am come to the Concluſion: The Advice of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> to the Fathers Aſſembled in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> preſently ſtrikes into my Mind; Advice worthy <hi>to be given with an Iron Pen and Lead in a Rock for ever;</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> in another caſe ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>The Biſhops from every quarter of the World Convened,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruf. lib</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Theodoſius lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> bring their ſeveral Complaints along with them; repreſent their Grievances, offer their Libels, and make their Appeals to the Emperour; as if the Diſturbance, rather than the Peace of the Church had been the Deſign of their Meeting. The good Emperour, not a little griev'd thereat, takes the Libels, ſeals them up, and holding them up in his Arms, pathetically deſires them to lay aſide all their private Animoſities, and with one Heart, to endeavour the Eſtabliſhment and Unity of the Church: committing withal, the reſpective Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels to the Fire; to the end, that neither they themſelves, nor their Poſterity, ſhould to their Scandal underſtand their Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It pleaſed Almighty God, that his Counſel was ſo well followed, as that their Debates were Calm; all the whole Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (ſix only excepted) unanimouſly agreeing in Condemnation of the Heretick and Hereſie, and the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>one Subſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this large Convention, wee'l ſuppoſe it no difficult matter to find out a parallel to the firſt part of this Narration. O that it might be happy in the like Succeſs and Concluſion! We are here met together, not in a <hi>School,</hi> but an <hi>Oratorie;</hi> not a place of <hi>Diſputation,</hi> but a <hi>Houſe of Prayer;</hi> not to ſettle the Faith, that's done to our Hands, but to make profeſſion of the Faith eſtabliſhed: Our Libellings,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171159:20"/>Heart-burnings and Diſſentions, are by ſo much the more intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and unreaſonable. In Diſputes, Heats may ariſe; we find the moſt Calm and Holy men Here to have exceeded due Bounds; betraying frequently more Paſſion than Reaſon. — In our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſemblies, and more Divine Worſhip, there ought to be none of theſe: We are here met in the Preſence of the Moſt High God, to receive Inſtruction, to offer up our Prayer and Praiſes to Him.— All thoſe Services require <hi>clean Hearts,</hi> and <hi>pure Hands.</hi> The Scholars of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports) after all their Bickerings and hot Conteſts, — in the cloſe of the day had their <hi>Reconciliations,</hi> ſtill parting lovingly and Friendly. We are the profeſſed Diſciples of a <hi>Great Maſter;</hi> O let not theſe Hearts riſe in judgment againſt us; let us remember, that this in an eſpecial manner among the <hi>Golden Doctrines</hi> of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our is recommended: <hi>Let not the Sun go down upon your Wrath.</hi> Wherefore condemn we from this moment, our Libels (as our good Emperour here, and the Primitive Converts did their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring Books) to the Flames. Let us forget our unhappy Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and remember our old Grudges no more; in the Dialect of the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>ult. Let all Bitterneſs and Wrath, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Clamour, and Evil-ſpeaking be put away from you; with all Malice; and be ye kind one to another, tender-hearted, forgiving one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> tells us, that the four firſt great Hereſies,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ. Pol. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>para.</hi> 54.</note> were by four general Councils in four words determined. I have and do propoſe unto you one word, which if well applied, is of ſo ſovereign a Balm, as to heal, not only ours, but all the wounds of Chriſtendome; and that is <hi>Charity. Above all put on Charity.</hi> By this we ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our own and others Sins, over-look Failings and Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; conquer Difficulties; and deſire nothing but God to all. The Evangeliſts relate, that the Crucifiers of our Saviour caſt Lots for his Garments; but St. <hi>John</hi> more particularly mentions the cauſe that induced them thereunto, <hi>John</hi> 19.23. <hi>Now his Coat was without Seam, Woven from the Top throughout, they ſaid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore among themſelves, let us not rent it, but caſt Lots for it, whoſe it ſhall be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon one of the Ancients hath an elegant Obſervation: <hi>The Mercileſs and Cruel Hang-men of</hi> Pilate, <hi>did not dare to attempt the rending of Chriſts ſeamleſs Coat: and wilt thou diſ-member the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171159:21"/>Church, which is One; divide Charity, which is God himſelf?</hi> He that blows the Coals of Contention, promotes or makes a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance in Chriſtian Society, does not only lacerate Chriſts ſeam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Garment; but tear in pieces his Body, rend his Spouſe; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues himſelf guilty of Barbarity beyond Compariſon greater than the former.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 13.8. urges an Argument for the reconciling all Differences between him and <hi>Lot,</hi> and their reſpective Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, from that near Relation in which they ſtood. <hi>Let there be no ſtrife I pray thee between me and thee, and between thy Herdſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and my Herdſ-men: for we are Brethren.</hi> If there be any weight in this (as we have great reaſon to believe) I am ſure it comes home to us with Improvement.</p>
               <p>We proceeded out of one common Stock, and ſo are <hi>Brethren.</hi> At the Font, we engaged in the ſame Baptiſmal Vow and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and ſo are <hi>Brethren.</hi> We met in this Holy place, profeſſing the ſame Faith, and practiſing the ſame Duties, and ſo are <hi>Brethren:</hi> our Houſes and Eſtates join to each other; we make up one Society, and ſo are <hi>Brethren.</hi> Therefore though our Herdſ-men <hi>for want of Breeding and Education quarrel,</hi> let there be no ſtrife between Us. O let us provoke one another to Love! and if there be any Contention, let it be, who ſhall exceed in Acts of Kindneſs; the only Emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on juſtifiable. Let us imitate the Ancients, who (as St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us) were of <hi>one accord, of one Heart, and one Soul,</hi> Acts 2.44, and 4.32. Let us <hi>put off the Old Man, and put on the New; as the Elect of God, Holy and Beloved Bowels of Mercies, Kindneſs, Humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering, Forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Forgiving one another; and above all, put on Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Chriſts ſake:— For the Goſpels ſake:— For our Souls ſake— For our Brethren and Companions ſake— For the ſake of our own preſent temporal Welfare and Quiet: Let us become New Creatures. So ſhall we find the two excellent Properties of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. meeting and conſpiring in our Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <hi>The Goodneſs and Pleaſantneſs of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, to the general bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> of all. Like the <hi>Dew of</hi> Hermon <hi>which fell upon the Hill of Sion,</hi> and <hi>that ſacred Oyntment which was poured out on the Head of</hi> Aaron to the Advantage of his Beard, and the Skirts of his Cloathing. So ſhall we be able to give Laws and Preſidents to the leſſer Villages round about us. So ſhall <hi>our Sons grow up as the young Plants, and our Daughters as the poliſhed Corners of the Temple; our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171159:21"/>Garners ſhall be full and plenteous of all manner of Store; our Sheep ſhall bring forth thouſands and ten thouſands in our Streets; our Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſhall be ſtrong to labour; there ſhall be no decay, no leading into Captivity, and no complaining in our Streets.</hi> So ſhall we grow ſweetly old in Love; live an Heaven upon Earth here, and be quietly tranſlated to that Kingdom, where the other Graces ceaſe, Charity ſtill continues.</p>
               <p>It remaineth, that with bended Knees and contrite Hearts, we all joyne in Prayer: Beſeeching that God, <hi>Who maketh men to be of one mind in an Houſe, yea, who maketh Wars to ceaſe in all the World; who breaketh the Bow, ſnappeth the Spear, and burneth the Chariot in the Fire: That he would be graciouſly pleaſed to put an end to all our unhappy Diviſions; to beat our Swords into Plow-ſhares, and our Spears into Pruning-hooks:</hi> That he would be pleaſed to give us <hi>one Heart, to put a new Spirit within us, to take away the Stony Heart out of our Fleſh, and to give us an Heart of Fleſh, that we may walk in his Statutes and keep his Ordinances.</hi> That we may be of <hi>one Mind, live in Peace;</hi> ſo ſhall <hi>the God of Love and Peace be with us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:171159:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books newly Printed for</hi> James Collins <hi>in</hi> Eſſex-Street <hi>without</hi> Temple-Bar.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE <hi>Reward of Diligence.</hi> By <hi>Lewis Sharp.</hi> 8o.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Confinement;</hi> an Ingenious Poem. 8o.</item>
               <item>A Letter from a Proteſtant Gentleman to a Lady revolted to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> 12o.</item>
               <item>A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>Dorothy St. Johns.</hi> By <hi>Antony Hornick</hi> Miniſter of the <hi>Savoy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Popery,</hi> or the Principles and Poſitions approved by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when really believed and practis'd, are very dangerous to All. And to Proteſtant Kings and Supreme Powers, more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally pernicious; and inconſiſtent with that Loyalty which by the Law of Nature and Scripture are due to Supreme Powers: In a Letter to a Perſon of Quality. By <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln. Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Diſcourſe of Truth.</hi> By the late Reverend Dr. <hi>Ruſt</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Downe</hi> and <hi>Connor.</hi> To which is added, <hi>The Way to Eternal Happineſs.</hi> By <hi>Joſeph Glanvil</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. 12o.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:171159:22"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
